Guide to the James G. McDonald Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
James G. McDonald Papers,
1838-1972 [
Bulk Dates: 1914-1962].
McDonald, James G. (James Grover), 1886-1964.
20 linear feet (47 document boxes; 1 oversize box)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#0818
4078520
This collection documents the professional and personal life of James Grover McDonald, a diplomat who worked extensively with refugee issues and served as the first U.S. ambassador to Israel.
Biographical Note
James Grover McDonald was born on November 29, 1886 in Coldwater, Ohio. His parents, Kenneth and Anna Dietrich McDonald, operated a hotel, and the family's five children worked alongside their parents. The family later moved to Albany, Indiana, to operate a second hotel, and there McDonald met Ruth Stafford, whom he would marry in 1915. The couple would have two daughters, Barbara Ann and Janet.
McDonald studied at Indiana University, earning an A.B. degree in 1909 and a master's in History, Political Science, and International Relations in 1910. He won a teaching fellowship in history at Harvard Graduate School and then returned to Indiana University in 1914 as assistant professor of history. He taught until 1918, with a break in 1915-1916 to visit Spain as a Harvard University traveling fellow. He also taught summer sessions in international affairs at the University of Georgia in 1916 and 1917.
At the recommendation of his Harvard advisors, McDonald moved to New York City and took a position with the Civil Service Reform Association, which was committed to ending government corruption. From 1919 to 1933, McDonald served as chairman of the Foreign Policy Association, an organization dedicated to educating the public about foreign affairs. McDonald presided over Foreign Policy Association Luncheons, which were broadcast over WEAF and NBC. During the late 1920s and early 1930s, he gave weekly talks on international relations over the same radio stations, speaking on current world events. McDonald traveled extensively and made trips to Germany nearly every year, experiencing Hitler's rise to power firsthand.
In 1933, McDonald became League of Nations High Commissioner for Refugees and was faced with the task of negotiating refugee possibilities with Germany prior to World War II. In a meeting with Hitler in 1933, he became aware of Nazi goals to exterminate the Jewish population. McDonald struggled to help Jews and other persecuted individuals leave Germany, but found that his ability was restrained by League policies. He was respected and admired for his efforts and was awarded the American Hebrew Medal for Promotion of Better Understanding between Christian and Jew in America.
In 1935, McDonald resigned from the position. In his resignation letter, he detailed the mistreatment of minorities in Germany and urged the League of Nations to take proactive measures not only to help refugees, but to recognize and address the problems in Germany that forced them to leave in the first place. The letter was widely circulated and was one of the first denouncements of the Nazi government by an international diplomat.
McDonald returned to New York, and from 1936 to1938 he worked on the editorial staff of the New York Times, specializing in editorials on international relations. In 1938 he returned to the problems of the refugees, serving as chairman of the President's Advisory Commission on Political Refugees. The Commission was involved mainly in working with the State Department to adapt immigration laws to the crisis in Germany. McDonald served on the Commission until 1945.
In 1946, McDonald served with the Anglo-American Committee of Inquiry on Palestine, a British and American committee charged with forming a policy on the admission of Jews into Palestine. McDonald traveled throughout the reason to hear the testimony of Jews and Palestinians, and became a strong supporter of unlimited immigration into Palestine by European refugees, and of the eventual creation of the state of Israel.
In 1948, President Truman asked McDonald to serve as a U.S. representative to Israel, and McDonald moved to the newly formed country along with his daughter, Barbara. The following year, he became the first U.S. ambassador to Israel and served for two years, working to forge a strong connection between the two countries during a period of upheaval. McDonald resigned as ambassador in 1951 and returned to the US, where he became chairman of the Advisory Council of the Development Corporation for Israel.
McDonald wrote about his personal experience as an ambassador in his book My Mission to Israel, published in 1951. His extensive diaries, now held by the U.S. Holocaust Memorial Museum in Washington, DC, have also been published in an annotated, multi-volume collection, The Diaries and Papers of James G. McDonald.
In addition to his long career in international affairs, McDonald was also a member of the Board of Education of the City of New York (1940-1942); president of the Brooklyn Institute of Arts and Sciences (1938-1942); and a member of the Harvard Club of New York.
James G. McDonald died in 1964.
Scope and Content
This collection documents the professional and personal life of James Grover McDonald, a diplomat who worked extensively on refugee issues and served as the first U.S. ambassador to Israel. Much of the material relates to McDonald's positions on the High Commission for Refugees (Jewish and Other) Coming from Germany and the Presidential Advisory Committee on Political Refugees. These files document international efforts to help minorities, primarily Jews, escape Germany prior to World War II. There is also a fair amount of information on McDonald's experience as U.S. ambassador to Israel. Materials include correspondence, speech and book drafts, pamphlets, photographs, and newspaper clippings.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into nine series:
Series I: Special Files, 1922-1972
Series II: General Correspondence, 1914-1962
Series III: Manuscripts and Speeches, 1914-1960
Series IV: High Commissioner for Refugees, 1933-1936
Series V: Presidential Advisory Committee on Political Refugees, 1936-1945
Series VI: Photographs and Papers, 1937-1961
Series VII: Development Corporation for Israel, 1951-1961
Series VIII: Pamphlets and Clipping Books, 1914-1951
Subseries VIII.1: Pamphlets, 1914-1951
Subseries VIII.2: Clipping Books, 1921-1939
Series IX: Research Files, 1838-1956.
Subjects
Herbert H. Lehman Collections (Columbia University).; United States.--President's Advisory Committee on Political Refugees.; National Broadcasting Company, inc.--Blue Network.; Foreign Policy Association.; Anglo-American Committee of Inquiry on Palestine.; Development Corporation for Israel.--Advisory Council.; New York Times Company.; High Commission for Refugees (Jewish and Other) Coming from Germany.; League of Nations.; McDonald, James G. (James Grover), 1886-1964.; Bentwich, Norman De Mattos, 1883-1971.; Inman, Samuel Guy, 1877-1965.; Kotschnig, Walter Maria, 1901-; Wurfbain, André L.; Israel.; United States--Diplomatic and consular service--Israel.; United States--Foreign relations--Israel.; Palestine--Politics and government.; World War, 1939-1945.; Holocaust.; Immigration policy and research.; International relations.; Refugees, Political.; Refugees--Germany.; Israel--Politics and government.; Ambassadors.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
1970 Correspondence, memoranda, documents, clippings
Gift of Mrs. James Grover McDonald, Mrs. Halsey V. Barrett, and Mrs. Archibald Stewart, 1972.
Related Material
James G. McDonalds's diaries are held at the U.S. Holocaust Memorial Museum in Washington, DC
Finding Aid available in repository and online; folder level control.
- Series I: Special Files, 1922-1972
  This series contains correspondence with prominent public figures, primarily politicians and government officials such as Dean Acheson, Henry Stimpson, and Harry Truman. The files were originally part of the general correspondence found in Series II, but were removed and housed separately. They are arranged alphabetically by correspondent name.
  - Acheson, Dean, 1945-1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Aldrich, Winthrop W, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Astor, Viscount and Viscountess (Nancy Langhorne), 1929-1931 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Baerwald, Paul, 1934-1961 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Baker, Newton D., 1932-1936 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Barrett, Edward Ware, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Baruch, Bernard M., 1932-1958 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ben-Gurion, David,1946-1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Benton, William, 1945-1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Berle, Adolph A., Jr., 1932-1943 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ben-Zvi, Itashak, 1954-1961 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Berlin, Irving, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bernstein, Leonard, 1949-1958 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Black, Hugo, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bloom, Sol, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bok, Curtis, 1928-1934 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bowles, Charles, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bradley, Omar, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Brandeis, Louis D., 1931-1934 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Brannan, Charles, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Brooks, Van Wyck, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1931-1946 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Byrnes, James, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Cantor, Eddie, 1937-1960 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Cardozo, Benjamin V., 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Celler, Emanuel, 1938-1949 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Chamberlain, Joseph P., 1933-1938 (4 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 27 to 30)
  - Chamberlain, Joseph P., 1939-1945 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Clay, Lucius D., 1949 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Cohen, Benjamin V., 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Clayton, William L, 1944-1946 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Coudert, Frederic R., 1933-1936 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Davies, Joseph E., 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Davis, Elmer, 1939-1954 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Davis, Norman, 1932-1942 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Dewy, Thomas E., 1942-1944 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Donovan, William J., 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Douglas, William O., 1948-1949,1960 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Dubinsky, David, 1940-1959 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Dulles, Allen W., 1942 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Dulles, John Foster, 1938-1954 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Eban, Abba, 1951-1961 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Einstein, Albert, 1933-1949 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight D., 1948-1954 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Eshkol, Levi, 1953-1961 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Ford, Henry, II, 1941,1944 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Forrestal, James V., 1945-1948 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Fosdick, Harry Emerson, 1933, 1948-1957 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Fosdick, Raymond B., 1933,1972 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Frank, Jerome N., 1938 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Frankfurter, Felix, 1933-1953 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Fulbright, J. William, 1946,1957 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Green, William, 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Harriman, W. Averell, 1943,1957 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Hayes, Carlton J.H., 1922-1945 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Herter, Christian A., 1942-1957 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Hoffman, Paul G., 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Hoover, Herbert, 1929-1954 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Hoover, J. Edgar, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - House, Edward M., 1932 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Hughes, Charles Evans, 1924-1930 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Hull, Cordell, 1933-1946 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Javits, Jacob K., 1949.1959 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Jessel, George, 1941-1945 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Jessup, Philip C., and Mrs. (Lois K.), 1932, 1941-1960 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Kennedy, Joseph P., 1938, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Kellog, Paul, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Kennedy, Joseph P., 1938, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Knopf, Alfred A., 1936,1947 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Kollek, Theodore, 1951-1958 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Krock, Arthur, 1939-1961 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - La Guardia, Fiorello, 1943-1946 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Lehman, Irving, 1935-1945 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Lamont, Thomas W., 1922-1944 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Laval, Pierre, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Leffingwell, Russell, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Lehman, Herbert, 1932-1961 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Leidesdorf, S.D. & Co., 1946-1961 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Lerner, Max, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Lindbergh, Charles A., 1944-1946 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Lippmann, Walter, 1933-1953 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Lodge, Henry Cabot, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Macdonald, J. Ramsey, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Magnes, Judah L., 1946 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Mann, Thomas, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Marshall, George C., 1948-1949 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Masaryk, Jan, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - McDonald, James G., 1928-1946 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - McNutt, Paul V., 1938, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Meir, Golda, 1961, 1958, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Mellon, Andrew W., 1930 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Meyer, Eugene, 1934-1961 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Moley, Raymond, 1932-1933, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Morgenthau, Henry, Sr. and Mrs., 1922, 1930-1937 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Morgenthau, Henry, Jr. and Mrs., 1939-1953 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Morgenthau, Henry III, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Murphy, Frank, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Murrow, Edward R., 1934-1935 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Nelson, Donald M., 1943 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Niebuhr, Reinhold, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Norris, George W., 1942 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Patterson, Robert P., 1943 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Poletti, Charles, 1936-1942 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Potofsky, Jacob S., 1949-1954 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Proskauer, Joseph M., 1939-1959 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Rabi, Isidor I., 1959 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Reid, Ogden R., 1952-1960 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Reid, Helen Rogers, 1948-1953 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Rickenbacker, Edward V., 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Robinson, Edward G., 1953-1954 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Rockefeller, David, 1939-1941 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Rockefeller, John D., Jr and John D. Rockefeller III, 1927-1958 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Rockefeller, Nelson A., 1942-1955 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin D., Jr., 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin D., 1932-1943 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1932-1936 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Roosevelt, James, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Rosenberg, Anna M., 1941-1949 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Rosenberg, James N., 1937-1961 (2 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 3 to 4)
  - Rosenberg, James N.--German Protest Poster, circa 1930s (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Rosenwald, William, 1935-196 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Salter, Sir Arthur, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Sarnoff, David, 1938-1959 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Schiff, Dorothy, 1952-1953 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Seligman, Eustace, 1932-1954 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Shotwell, James T., 1932-1953 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Silver, Abba Hillel, 1949-1960 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Silver, Charles H., 1954-1960 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Spellman, Francis Cardinal, 1949, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Stettinius, Edward R., 1943-1946 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Stimson, Henry L., 1930-1933, 1942-1946 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Stone, Dewey D., 1950-1961 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Straus, Roger W., 1948-1954 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Straus, Lewis L., 1934-1959 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Taylor, Myron C, 1941-1953 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Sulzberger, Arthur H., 1932-1957 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Swope, Gerald, 1936, 1949-1958 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Swope, Herbert Bayard, 1934, 1945-1951 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Taft, Robert A., 1939-1944, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Thomas, Norman, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Thompson, Dorothy, 1936-1942 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Truman, Harry S., 1944-1961 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Vandenberg, Arthur H., 1945-1948 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Wagner, Robert, Sr., 1934, 1945-1949 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Wald, Lillian, 1933-1936 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Warburg, Felix M., 1933-1934 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Warburg, Edward M. M., 1940-1960 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Warburg, Felix M., 1935-1936 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Warburg, Frieda Schiff, 1933, 1948-1958 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Weizmann, Chaim, 1945-1955 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Welles, Sumner, 1942-1952 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Whalen, Grover, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Wilkie, Wendell L, 1939-1947 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Weizmann Institute, 1952-1959 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Wise, Stephen S., 1934-1949 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Young, Owen D., 1928-1933 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Series II: General Correspondence, 1914-1962
  The correspondence in this series spans most of McDonald's life, but much of the material dates from after World War II and relates to McDonald's involvement with the Anglo-American Committee of Inquiry on Palestine, the formation of Israel, and his experience as U.S. ambassador to Israel. There is also considerable material relating to refugees, as well as some personal correspondence with family and friends. Files are arranged alphabetically by correspondent or institution name.
  - A (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Abrams, Benjamin (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Alfange, Dean (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - American Embassy
    - Furnishing (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Personal Finances (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Invitation Lists (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Press Clippings (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - American Friends Service Committee (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - American Jewish Congress (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - American Palestine Campaign (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - A.A.C.I.P
    - European Diary, circa 1946 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - European Trip, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - European Trip--Status Reports, 1946 (Box 48, Folder 1)
    - Palestine (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - U.S. Material (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Related U.N. Material (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Governments and Organizations--General (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Report to U.S. and U.K. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Arvery, Jacob M., 1949-1961 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Assistance Medicale
    - Eddie Cantor Appeal (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Promotional Scrapbook (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Aydelotte, Frank, 1945-1947 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Ba-Bn (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Baer, Arthur, 1945-1949 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Balaban, Barney, 1949-1952 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Baldwin, Hanson W., 1949 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Bar-Ilan University (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Barkley, Alben W., 1948-1950 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Bentwich, Norman, 1934-1961 (Box 8, Folder 5 to 8)
  - Berry, Burton Y., 1950-1951 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Biddle, Francis, 1938-1945 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Billikopf, Jacob, 1946-1947 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Blank, Sam, 1946-1961 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Blaustein, Jacob, 1946-1960 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Bo-Bz (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Board of Education, NYC (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Bolles, Blair, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Borchard, Edwin M., 1932 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Brewster, Owen, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Bronfman, Samuel, 1946-1960 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Brown, Charles, 1945-1959 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Buck, Ellsworth, 1944-1948 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Bullitt, William C., 1934-1942 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Bunche, Ralph J., 1949-1959 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - C (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Cantor, Eddie, 1937-1960 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Catholic Church (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Cecil of Chelwood, Viscount, 1933-1946 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Clifford, Clark, 1947-1953 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Connelly, Matthew J., 1948-1949 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Connelly, Tom, 1948 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Council on Foreign Relations (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Cox, Oscar, 1944 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Crank File (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Crosgrave, Lloyd M. (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Crossman, Richard H.S., 1947 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Crum, Bartley C., 1946-1956 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - D--Oversize (Box 48, Folder 6)
  - D (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - D'Avigdor-Goldsmid, Sir Henry, 1936-1960 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Davis, Monnett B., 1951-1953 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Dayan, Moshe, 1954-1959 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - De Botton, Gilbert, 1952-1956 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - De Los Rios, Fernando, 1937 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Department of State (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - De Rothschild, Baron Guy, 1949-1956 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - De Rothschild, Baron Robert, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Diplomatic Corps--Israel (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Dodd, William E., 1934 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Douglas, Paul H., 1956 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Dunn, James C., 1948 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - E (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Eichelberger, Clark, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Elmhirst, Mrs. Leonard, 1934 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Emergency Committee in Aid of German Scholars (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Empire State Bldg. Office (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Esco Foundation for Palestine Inc. (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Ethrige, Mark, 1949 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Ewing, Oscar R., 1943-1954 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Eylath, Eliahu, 1958 (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Eytan, Walter, 1949-1960 (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - F (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Farley, James A., 1940-1954 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - C.C.--James L. Fly, 1942-1944 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Feinberg, Abraham, 1949-1958 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Flynn, Edward J., 1941-1945 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Forbes, W. Cameron, 1930 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Ford, Richard, 1950-1951 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Foreign Policy Association
    - General (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Commendatory Letters, 1929-1933 (2 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 8 to 9)
  - Frank, Gerold, 1950-1959 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Gardner, John W., 1953 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Ga-Gol (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - George, Mr. and Mrs. Robert, 1914-1915 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - German University League (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - German Society of Chicago--Louis Guenzel (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Glueck, Nelson, 1946-1959 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Goldman, Emanuel, 1948-1961 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Goldman, Norman, 1951-1958 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Goldstein, Israel, 1935-1962 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Goldwater, Monroe, 1945- 1949 (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Gom-Gz (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Good, Ann Campbell, 1945 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Grandi, Dino, 1932 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Grayzel, Soloman, 1959-1960 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Griffis, Stanton, 1948-1949 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Grossinger, Jennie, 1951-1958 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - H (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Hadassah (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Hammett, Dashiel, 1938 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Harazi, Shalom,1951-1960 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Harkness, Edward H., 1934 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Harman, Avraham, 1951-1961 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Harvard University and Harvard Club (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Herold, Sidney, 1947-1950 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Herzog, Yaacov, 1950-1960 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Hexter, Maurice, 1958-1961 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Hilldring, John, 1947-1959 (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Hisws, Alger, 1946 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Hopkins, Harry, 1945 (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Hudson, Manley O., 1917 (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Humphrey, Hubert H., 1956-1959 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Hutcheson, Joseph C., Jr.1946-1957 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - I (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Indiana University (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Ingersoll, Raymond V. and Mrs., 1934-1943 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Israel
    - Artists (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Personal Finances (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - J (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Jackson, C.D., 1953 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Jacobson, Eddie, 1948-1955 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - James, Edwin, 1951 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Jones, Jesse, 1942 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Joseph, Dov, 1951 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - K (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Kaplan, Eliezer and Mrs., 1951-1959 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Karlin Family, 1947-1959 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Kerner, Otto, 1961 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Kintner, Robert E., 1945 (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Knox, Charles, 1949-1961 (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Kohn, Leo, 1953-1960 (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Krinizi, A., 1949-1955 (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - Kuper, S.M., 1954-1959 (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - L (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Lawson, Edward B., 1955-1959 (Box 14, Folder 2)